Hi, this is Matt Baker. On this channel,
we have a 3-hour long video explaining
the Christian denominations family tree
in great detail using this chart.
However, a simplified version of the
same thing is also included on our world
religions family tree. But as of yet,
I've never gone through it in a video.
So today, that's what I'm going to do in
let's just say far less than 3 hours.
Take note, if you want to get a copy of
either of these wall charts, just head
over to useful charts. com or click the
link in the description or pinned
comment. So obviously, Christianity
starts with Jesus, who lived from
approximately 4 BCE to 30 CE. Since
Jesus was a Jew, most of his original
followers were also Jews, and they came
from several different branches of
Second Temple Judaism. Originally, those
belonging to the new movement started by
Jesus were simply called the followers
of the way. But pretty soon, more and
more non-Jews started to join. And thus,
the movement eventually came to be seen
as a completely new religion. Initially,
Christianity drew heavily from a group
of people known as God-fearers. These
were Greeks and Romans who were
attracted to Jewish ideas, but did not
want to fully convert to Judaism due to
all of the various rules involved. Well,
Christianity had far fewer requirements.
For example, no circumcision and no
dietary restrictions. And therefore, it
was much easier for God-fearers to
convert to Christianity. So many of them
did. I should also point out that while
Christianity was mostly built upon
Jewish ideas, it also inherited certain
ideas from Greek philosophy. Okay, so
another important thing to know is that
in its early days, there was not really
just one Christianity, but rather many
Christianities.
From the perspective of the Christianity
that eventually became dominant, which
I've labeled Proto-Orthodox
Christianity, all of the other
Christianities were heresies that had to
be stamped out. One of the big ones was
Gnosticism, which eventually did die
out, but ended up influencing both
Manichaeism and Mandaeism. There were
also the Ebionites and Nazarenes, who
were mostly Jewish Christians who saw
Jesus [clears throat] as the Messiah,
but not as God. They too died out, but
likely had an influence on the
development of Islam. The final
alternative to what became the dominant
form of Christianity was Arianism, which
taught that Jesus was a created being
who was elevated to the position of God.
The controversy over this led to the
Council of Nicaea in 325, in which
Arianism was rejected, and the official
set of Christian beliefs was written
down, resulting in what is known today
as the Nicene Creed. According to Nicene
Christianity, Jesus and the Father are
co-equal and co-eternal. Now, a couple
decades later in 380, Nicene
Christianity was made the official state
religion of the Roman Empire. But you
see, by that point, there were also
Christians outside of the Roman Empire,
particularly to the east in the Sasanid
Persian Empire. Thus, around this time,
the Church of the East was established
as a distinct group. From here, the main
church, the one that existed within the
Roman Empire, went on to be organized
into five main patriarchs, each in a
major city. Rome, Constantinople,
Antioch, which is in Syria, Jerusalem,
and Alexandria, which is in Egypt. And
the thing is, there ended up being a bit
of disagreement between these areas. In
Rome and Constantinople, an additional
creed, known as the Chalcedonian Creed,
was adopted, and it clarified that
although Jesus was equal to God, he had
two separate natures, one divine and one
human. However, the other three
pentarchies did not accept this creed,
arguing instead that Jesus had only one
nature, which was both divine and human
at the same time. The division between
the Chalcedonians and the
non-Chalcedonians, who became known as
Oriental Orthodox, became even more
distinct when all three of the
non-Chalcedonian areas were taken over
by Islam. Christianity continued to
exist in those areas, but was now in the
minority. Today, the Syriac Orthodox
Church, the Coptic Orthodox Church in
Egypt, and the Ethiopian Orthodox
Tewahedo Church, all trace their roots
to the three non-Chalcedonian
patriarchates from the Roman era. In
Rome and Constantinople, though,
Christianity continued to be the
majority religion, and thus it was these
two cities that continued to be the main
centers of Christianity. For several
more centuries, Christianity in these
two areas continued to be united, but
eventually they split. The area under
Rome's jurisdiction became known as the
Catholic Church, and to this day, it is
still led by the Patriarch of Rome,
although he's now better known as the
Pope. Whereas the area under
Constantinople's jurisdiction became
known as the Orthodox Church, still led
by the Patriarch of Constantinople.
Today, the largest branch of the
Orthodox Church is actually the Russian
Orthodox Church, which in 2018 cut ties
with Constantinople. Okay, for the rest
of the chart, we'll be looking at the
many denominations that came about as a
result of the Protestant Reformation. It
started in 1517 as a reform movement
within the Catholic Church, but quickly
led to the creation of three new
branches of Christianity, mostly along
state lines. Lutheranism, based on the
teachings of Martin Luther, became
dominant in many German states, as well
as in Scandinavia. Calvinism, based on
the teachings of John Calvin, became
dominant in the Dutch Republic and
Scotland. And finally, Anglicanism
became dominant in England. Take note
that the Calvinist branch is also known
as the Reformed branch, and that
Calvinist churches that trace their
roots to Scotland are known as
Presbyterians.
Now, there was also a fourth Protestant
movement early on that was even more
radical. Its followers became known as
Anabaptists because they taught that
adults should be rebaptized. Groups that
trace their roots to this movement
include the Brethren, the Mennonites,
[clears throat] and the Amish. Okay,
from here on out, we'll mostly be
dealing with the English-speaking world.
At first, Great Britain, and then mostly
the United States. Since Anglicanism
continued to operate a lot like
Catholicism, meaning that it had a very
top-down structure, a bunch of smaller,
more loosely organized church groups
eventually started to pop up as well.
Collectively, the people belonging to
these groups were known as English
separatists, and many of them ended up
traveling to the Americas, where they
could have more religious freedom.
However, most of the original groups,
such as the Puritans, eventually fizzled
out. But two that didn't were the
Quakers and the Baptists. We'll be
coming back to the Baptists in a moment,
but for now, take note that there were
also many congregations that simply
remained independent, hence the term
Congregationalists.
We now come to the first of the three
Great Awakenings. These were periods of
increased religious fervor that led to
the creation of even more new
denominations. Now, although the
Baptists were around before this time,
it wasn't really until the First Great
Awakening that their numbers really
started to grow. For example, it was at
this point that many Congregationalists,
inspired by all the increased religious
fervor, began to identify as Baptist.
The other big denomination connected to
the First Great Awakening is the
Methodist Church. It was primarily built
by former Anglicans, most notably a man
named John Wesley. Okay, around 80 years
later, there was a Second Great
Awakening. And this time, things took
place exclusively in the United States.
It attracted mainly Congregationalists,
Baptists, and Methodists, but then
shuffled many of them into new
denominations, such as the Disciples of
Christ and the Plymouth Brethren.
However, the three largest denominations
that came about as a result of the
Second Great Awakening are the
Seventh-day Adventists, the Jehovah's
Witnesses, and the Mormons. They differ
from other denominations in that they
all departed from traditional Nicene
Christianity. This is why they are shown
in beige instead of purple, except for
the Seventh-day Adventists, as they have
since moved back towards Nicene beliefs.
All right, finally we come to the Third
Great Awakening, which initially started
out as a movement among Methodists,
leading to the creation of the Holiness
churches. However, perhaps more
importantly, following the Azusa Street
Revival in Los Angeles, it also led to
the Pentecostal movement, and in turn
the Charismatic movement, both of which
are associated with speaking in tongues.
But another key aspect of the Third
Great Awakening was the rise of
fundamentalism, which involves very
literal interpretations of scripture and
very conservative viewpoints. While not
a denomination of its own,
fundamentalism is followed by many
Pentecostals and by many Baptists. At
the other end of the spectrum is the
very liberal United Church of Christ,
which traces its roots back to the many
independent Congregationalist groups
from early American history. Okay, so
that was a very quick overview of the
Christian denominations family tree.
Like I say, if you want a much deeper
dive, you can check out the 3-hour long
video we made on the same topic. And if
you want to get a copy of either the
World Religions family tree or the
Christian denominations family tree, be
sure to visit our website,
usefulcharts.com.
Thanks for watching.